let us first see what the problem is
with cache coherence that is do we even
need cache coherence our programmer is
expecting to see shared memory behavior
that means that when one core writes
let's say 15 to a variable and then
another core reads that variable it will
read what the last right put there this
is how cores communicate through shared
memory one writes something to a shared
memory address another one reads it and
expects to see the data that was written
there but in our Hardware each core has
its own cache and we need cores to have
their own caches at least in the level
one because a single large level one
cache would be too slow and would not
have enough trut to keep up with the
request from all of the cores so because
we cannot do this we have private or per
core L1 caches so each core has its own
however once you have this private
caches here is what can happen this is
the core a with a level one cache for
core a this is core B and it has its own
level one cache so we said that let's
say core a writes xal 15 suppose this is
a cach Miss we use the address of x to
index into our cache check the tag
whether it corresponds to X and then if
this is a cach Miss we go to our main
memory and fetch the whole block into
our cache let's say that in this block X
is is zero once we fetch it into our
cache we write our 15 here so now we
have a 15 in our cach here now let's say
that core B wants to read X so it wants
to see what x is it uses the address of
x to index into its own cache sees that
it doesn't have what it's looking for
there and reads the block from Main
memory this block here has zero forx
still because we didn't write back from
a cach yet so we end up reading zero
which is not correct and know that this
doesn't occur only the first time when
we have a cache Miss from now on a can
write to its own L1 cache many many
times B can read from its own cache many
many times a will keep writing to its
cache and not updating memory B will
keep reading from its cache and not
checking back from memory because once
we bring it into the cash is going to be
a hit B is never modifying it it's
always going to read zero no matter how
many times a writes 15 or something else
here so obviously we are not getting the
communication of data we want from A's
rights to B's reads and thus our shared
memory doesn't work when we get in a
shared memory system Behavior like this
we say that it is
incoherent the same memory location as
seen from different cores can have have
different values which is not what
should be happening in a shared memory
in order to not get a incoherent system
we need an active approach to Cache
coherence that will make this whole
thing behave as a single memory even
though in reality there are multiple
copies of the data floating around